

UZMAR DE JESÚS GÓMEZ YÁÑEZ

CURRICULUM VITAE

DATA SCIENTIST I AT RACKSPACE TECHNOLOGY, BSC IN PHYSICS

PERSONAL STATEMENT

Learned to program throughout the Physics career, mainly in topics of scientific computing. Hands-on experience applying Machine Learning algorithms to real business problems. Excellent usage of GNU / Linux systems and knowledge of several object-oriented programming languages such as Python and C++. I have also worked in the academic field as a teacher assistant, teaching mathematics, computer science and physics topics at a university level. Good understanding of algorithms and data structures.

PERSONAL DATA

Address: Mexico City, Mexico Phone: +52 5539347885

EMAIL: uzmar.gomez@ciencias.unam.mx
LINKEDIN: www.linkedin.com/in/uzmargomez
GITHUB: https://github.com/uzmargomez

EDUCATION

Physics

2018 | Bachelor of Science in PHYSICS, Faculty of Science, National Autonomous University of Mexico

(UNAM), Mexico City, Mexico.

2011 Thesis: "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric"

Description: Creation of a finite differences scheme that evolves the relativistic Vlasov equation on a black hole metric background, assuming this is an advective equation, with velocities

dependent both on time and position.

Advisor: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

OVERALL SCORE: 9.37/10 Detailed List of Grades

Computer Science

2010 | Technical Career in COMPUTER SCIENCE, ENP Nº 7 National Autonomous University of Mexico

(UNAM), Mexico City, Mexico.

2008 OVERALL SCORE: 9.1/10 Detailed List of Grades

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages | Python, C/C++, Fortran, Julia, Go

Machine/Deep Learning | TensorFlow, Keras, PyTorch, Facebook Prophet, ARIMA, SARIMA, LDA, PCA,

Recommendation systems, Classification problems

Databases | SQL, MongoDB | Containers | Docker, Kubernetes

Operating Systems | Debian GNU/Linux, Ubuntu GNU/Linux, Windows

Web Backend | Flas

Web Frontend | HTML, Bootstrap

Version Control | Git

Parallel Computing | CUDA C/C++, CUDA Python

Data Visualization | Tableau, Qlik

GCP Tools (Console and CLI) | BigQuery, Compute Engine, Composer, Container Registry, Kubernetes En-

gine, Storage, Data Studio

LANGUAGES

ENGLISH: C1 Level - Duolingo English Test (2020), B2 Level - IELTS (2018)

SPANISH: Mothertongue

INTERESTS AND ACTIVITIES

Academic

Data Science, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Numerical Analysis, Competitive Programming, General Relativity, Numerical Relativity, Gravitational Waves, Black Holes, Quantum Mechanics, Computer Science, Electromagnetism. *Non academic*

Running, Swimming, Playing the Guitar, Science Fiction and Fantasy Reading, Traveling, Videogames.

EXPERIENCE

Short Description

Jul 2020 - Present. I'm currently working as a Data Scientist I at Rackspace Technology. I helped on the migration of data from on-premises servers to the GCP cloud. I have used Big Query for consulting, and Data Studio for data exploration. I am working on a way to create a churn prediction model that uses a feature related to the COVID19 spreading aside from other business-related features.

Dec 2019 - Jun 2020. I worked on a face recognition system using a method called Sparse Representation and another one using Neural Networks. I acquired a deep understanding of Neural Networks for Face Detection and Recognition, Image Classification, Language Processing, among others. Also, I have some experience in Data Visualization tools such as Tableau.

Sep 2019 - Dec 2019. Data Scientist Trainee at Softtek. I learned about different statistical and machine learning techniques, as well as algorithms, to study a wide variety of problems.

2012 - 2019. As mentioned below, I have taught Computer Science classes, in which the Python programming language was introduced to Physics students.

Sep 2018 - Dec 2019. I have research experience using the Einstein Toolkit, a software platform created for advancing and supporting research in relativistic astrophysics and gravitational physics.

Subjects I have taught:

- Computer Science.
 https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/102.pdf
- Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation 1. https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/docencia/horarios/presentacion/295997
- Relativity https://web.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/718.pdf
- Mathematics I for Applied Sciences.
 http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1118.pdf
- Mathematics II for Applied Sciences.
 http://www.fciencias.unam.mx/asignaturas/1216.pdf

Technical

PRESENT JUL 2020	Data Scientist I at RACKSPACE TECHNOLOGY Mexico City, Mexico.
-	Data Scientist at SOFTTEK Mexico City, Mexico.
DEC 2019 SEP 2019	Data Scientist Trainee at SOFTTEK Mexico City, Mexico.

Vocational

Vocacionai		
Semester 2019-2	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	o Mathematics II for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2019-1	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	Selected Topics in Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation IMathematics I for Applied Sciences	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2018-2	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	RelativityMathematics II for Applied Sciences	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2018-1	Teacher Assistant B at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	RelativityMathematics I for Applied Sciences	Dr. Miguel Alcubierre MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2017-2	Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	Mathematics II for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Semester 2017-1	Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	 Mathematics I for Applied Sciences Computer Science	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal MSc. Alejandro Villarreal
Jun 2017	Teacher at Coordination of Programs of Differenti- ated Attention for Students, Faculty of Engineering, UNAM	
	Mexico City, Mexico. • Electrodynamics with an introduction to special relativity	Eng. Raúl Puente
Semester 2016-1	Teacher Assistant A at FACULTY OF SCIENCE, UNAM Mexico City, Mexico.	
	Mathematics I for Applied Sciences	MSc. Alejandro Villarreal

Conferences, Courses, Schools and Workshops Attended

Computer Scie	nce Related
Ост 09, 2020	Conference. THE Data Science Conference
Ост 08, 2020	Online conference due to COVID19
,	https://www.thedatascienceconference.com
	•
Ост 09, 2020	Course. Building Resilient Streaming Analytics Systems on GCP (COURSERA)
Ост 08, 2020	Google Cloud Platform
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	ZNG729Z9L78P
OCT 08, 2020	Course. Modernizing Data Lakes and Data Warehouses with GCP (COURSERA)
OCT 07, 2020	Google Cloud Platform
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	JUDDNMKRSBUA
ОСТ 07, 2020	Course. Building Batch Data Pipelines on GCP (COURSERA)
SEP 10, 2020	Google Cloud Platform
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	8KTYPM3GZQS7
SEP 10, 2020	Course. Smart Analytics, Machine Learning, and AI on GCP (COURSERA)
SEP 10, 2020 SEP 01, 2020	Google Cloud Platform
3EP 01, 2020	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	LAZ8CNLM2M5A
Ago 09, 2020	Course. Google Cloud Platform Big Data and Machine Learning Fundamentals
	(COURSERA)
AGO 01, 2020	Google Cloud Platform
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	S9HSH92LSALR
Jun 19, 2020	Course. Convolutional Neural Networks in TensorFlow (COURSERA)
Jun 15, 2020	DeepLearning.ai
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	76LGX8GCUG5D
lun 15 2020	Course Introduction to Toursellow for Artificial Intelligence Machine Learning
Jun 15, 2020	Course. Introduction to TensorFlow for Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, and Deep Learning (COURSERA)
lus 15 2020	DeepLearning (COOKSERA)
Jun 15, 2020	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	LZJ2FSW2RJGP
	LESZFOWZROGF
MAY 04, 2020	Course . Al & Deep Learning with TensorFlow (EDUREKA)
MAR 04, 2020	Edureka! For Business
•	https://www.edureka.co/lms/certificate/c3d0ebdc5518b429f6cc1a009454a9df
	•
MAR 26, 2020	Specialization. Accelerated Computer Science Fundamentals (COURSERA)
Ago 04, 2019	University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/specialization/
	certificate/DRF2CVM7P7FB
MAR 26, 2020	Course. Unordered Data Structures (COURSERA)
SEP 15, 2019	University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	DFHE5FBHVAAD
MAD 04 2020	Course. Python Statistics for Data Science Course (EDUREKA)
MAR 04, 2020 FEB 10, 2020	Edureka! For Business
166 10, 2020	https://www.edureka.co/lms/certificate/8a0976c4e21d5bee00ff053e2d8e3f3e
	noops.,,, www.odd.odd.oo, imb, ool olliodoo, odoo oo lollidoosoosii oo ool oo lollidoo
SEP 15, 2019	Course. Ordered Data Structures (COURSERA)
Ago 11, 2019	University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	PZ9NABHA7XBY
Ago 11, 2019	Course. Object-Oriented Data Structures in C++ (COURSERA)
Ago 04, 2019	University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign
	https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/
	2YKIIRK8T.I.I5R

2YKURK8TJJ5B

Jul 29, 2019 Jun 02, 2019	Course. Algorithmic Toolbox (COURSERA) University of California San Diego, National Research University Higher School of Economics https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/FBZ5SK3E9BB6
APR 17, 2019 APR 03, 2019	Course. Operating Systems and You: Becoming a Power User (COURSERA) Grow with Google, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ V6STDES4HLPE
Mar 10, 2019 Mar 08, 2019	Course. Python Data Structures (COURSERA) University of Michingan, Michigan, United States. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ L6Y7MZQDAJHP
FEB 26, 2019 FEB 21, 2019	Course. Programming for Everybody (Getting Started with Python) (COURSERA) University of Michingan, Michigan, United States. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ CNNYCJB5YB46
FEB 14, 2019 FEB 03, 2019	Course. Technical Support Fundamentals (COURSERA) Grow with Google, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ YQRPQLC86CUM
FEB 5, 2019 FEB 3, 2019	Course. Introduction to Data Science: Statistical Programming with R (COURSERA) National Autonomous University of Mexico, Mexico City, Mexico. https://www.coursera.org/account/accomplishments/certificate/ E75DVAG2956T
Jun 13, 2018 Jun 9, 2018	School. Deep Learning and Multimessenger Astronomy Tecnológico de Monterrey, Guadalajara, Mexico.
Jan 27, 2017 Jan 16, 2017	Course. Basic Linux Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.
Jul 01, 2016 Jun 20, 2016	Course. Fortran Fundamentals Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.
Physics Related	
Nov 11, 2018	School . Third Meeting of the Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves.
Nov 9, 2018	Playa del Carmen, Quintana Roo, Mexico.
Nov 9, 2018	School . Third School of Relativity and Gravitational Waves. XII School of the Division of Gravitation and Mathematical Physics.
Nov 5, 2018	Playa del Carmen, Quintana Roo, Mexico.
Aug 12, 2017 Aug 10, 2017	Workshop. Fifth Gravitation and Cosmology Workshop. Institute of Physical Sciences UNAM, Cuernavaca, Mexico.
Aug 9, 2017 Aug 7, 2017	School . Second School of Relativity and Gravitational Waves. Institute of Physical Sciences UNAM, Cuernavaca, Mexico.
Jan 18, 2016 Jan 7, 2016	Course. Introduction to Relativistic Electrodynamics Faculty of Engineering UNAM, Mexico City, Mexico.

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIP

SEP 2019 Fellow JAN 2017 Thematic Network of Black Holes and Gravitational Waves (Red ANyOG, CONACYT). Student Associate DEC 2019 Jan 2016 Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM. JAN 2016 Student Associate

VOLUNTEER ACTIVITIES

JAN 2015

SEP 2019 Teacher MAR 2019 University Student Council (CEU México) Provide university students with tools to help develop their academic, professional and personal skills, to facilitate their employment and the definition of their life project. MAR 2019 Volunteer **SEP 2018** Adopt a Talent Program (PAUTA)

Encourage scientific vocation so that those children and adolescents who like science, as well as those with outstanding skills, find a space where they can share their interest and learn from each other.

Institute of Physics, UNAM.

PRESENTATIONS AND POSTER SESSIONS

OCT 11, 2017 Poster Presentation at LX NATIONAL CONGRESS OF PHYSICS.

Monterrey, Mexico

Presentation of a poster about my undergraduate thesis "Numerical Study of Vlasov Equation in the Schwarzschild Metric".

SCHOLARSHIPS, AWARDS, HONORS AND ACCOMPLISHMENTS

2017 Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Proyect Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT). 2016 Scholarship awarded for Conclusion of Undergraduate School 2016 Support Program for Research Projects and Technological Innovation (PAPIIT). 2015

REFERENCES

NAME: Dr. Charles Mueller

INSTITUTION NAME: Rackspace Technology, USA

> OCCUPATION: Data Scientist IV

> > EMAIL: charles.mueller@rackspace.com

Dr. Fernando Herrera NAME: INSTITUTION NAME: Softtek, Mexico Senior Data Scientist OCCUPATION:

> fernandoj.herrera@softtek.com EMAIL:

Dr. Alejandro Villarreal NAME: Faculty of Science, UNAM. INSTITUTION NAME:

OCCUPATION: Researcher, Teacher

> EMAIL: alejandro.v@ciencias.unam.mx

NAME: Dr. Miguel Alcubierre

INSTITUTION NAME: Institute of Nuclear Sciences, UNAM.

Director, Researcher, Teacher OCCUPATION: EMAIL: malcubi@nucleares.unam.mx

Bachelor of Science in Physics

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) Grades

Course	GRADE	CREDITS
Differential and Integral Calculus I	07	18
Algebra	10	10
Computer Science	10	6
Analytic Geometry I	08	10
Differential and Integral Calculus II	10	18
Contemporary Physics	09	6
Vector Mechanics	9	12
Analytic Geometry II	09	10
Mechanics Laboratory	10	6
Collective Phenomena	10	12
Collective Phenomena Laboratory	09	6
Linear Algebra I	10	10
Differential Equations I	08	10
Optics	09	12
Linear Algebra II	10	10
Differential and Integral Calculus III	07	18
Electromagnetism I	9	12
Electromagnetism Laboratory	10	6
Tensor Calculus	9	10
Differential and Integral Calculus IV	07	18
Introduction to Quantum Physics	10	12
Optics Laboratory	10	6
Thermodynamics	09	12
Advanced Mathematics of Physics	10	10
Computational Physics	10	12
Quantum Mechanics	09	12
Complex Variable I	10	10
Selected Topics of Mathematics and Theoretical Physics	10	6
Electromagnetism II	08	12
Electronics Laboratory	10	6
Statistical Physics	10	12
Contemporary Physics Laboratory I	10	6
Complex Variable II	10	10
Analytical Mechanics	10	12
Relativity	09	06
Introduction to Elementary Particle Physics I	10	06
Dynamics of Deformable Bodies	10	12
Atomic Physics and Condensed Matter	09	06
Nuclear and Subnuclear Physics	09	06
Contemporary Physics Laboratory II	10	06
Topology and Differential Geometry for Physics	10	06
Selected Topics of Relativity, Cosmology and Gravitation I	10	06
Selected Topics of Computational Physics I	10	06
English Language	AC	00
	Total Credits	418
	OVERALL SCORE	9.37

Technical Career in Computer Science

National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) Grades

Course GRADE Introduction to Computer Science 9 Operating Systems 10 General Use Aplications 9 Problem Solving and Programming Techniques 9 Structured Programming 10 **Event-Oriented Programming** Systems Analysis and Design 10 Database-Oriented Programming 6 Local Area Networks 9 Preventive Maintenance and Minor Corrections for PC's 10 **OVERALL SCORE** 9.1